<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Churches complaint against sacriledge, or, Sacriledge truely dissected and layed open wherein is briefly shewn 1. The just collation, 2. The unjust ablation of the riches and honours of the clergy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35594</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15479822</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15479822</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1148:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Churches complaint against sacriledge, or, Sacriledge truely dissected and layed open wherein is briefly shewn 1. The just collation, 2. The unjust ablation of the riches and honours of the clergy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Sacrilege.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103554:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Churches COMPLAINT Againſt SACRILEDGE OR Sacriledge truely Diſſected and layed open.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is briefly ſhewn:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Juſt Collation, 2. The unjuſt Ablation of the Riches and Honours of the CLERGY.</p>
            <q>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, Doeſt thou commit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Yeer 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103554:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103554:2"/>
            <head>OF Sacriledge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eligion is as the Poles of the World, or that <hi>Atlas,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> which (the Poets ſay) holds up Heaven;<note place="margin">The neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in State<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it ſtands on Earth and reacheth God. It is that which poiſeth Societies and States below; for without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of a Providence, to overſee and reckon with us, might, craft, and falſhood would ſway in the world alike with Men and Beaſts; the conſcience of good and evill would be all one. And it is that which enobleth man, erects his affections, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates him in a happineſſe above nature: and in a word, it procures all bleſſings upon us. So that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we aime at a Spirituall, or (which is more to theſe times) a civill weale only, Religion is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be magnified.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> And as Religion upholds States, the Prieſt uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, after the inward vertue of the Doctrine it ſelf,<note place="margin">Of the prieſt to Religion.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103554:3"/>is he upholds Religion. Religion can neither plant nor ſuſtaine it ſelfe alone, and what ſupport ſoever it have from the Prince, or the laws of a Nation, the Prieſt is as the ſoule of that power; all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Ceremonies have their life from him; and it is our conſent in his holy Calling, that keeps us from the ſingularitie of our owne imaginations. Though man of himſelf be Religious, to make men conſpire in one Religion, they muſt have ſome thing ſingular to hold to. Though there may bee Religion, and a Congregation, there can hardly be a Church, where there is no Precentor.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 
               <note place="margin">Of the meanes to ſet up the Prieſt.</note>Now the gifts whereby the Prieſt retaines our reverence, are either Spirituall or Supernaturall, as of Propheſiing and working Miracles; or Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Externall, as the endowments and gloryes of this World: whereof the former ſhew where God is, the later where he hath been: and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer proceed immediately from the Spirit, in the later men may concurre.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> 
               <note place="margin">The order of theſe meanes in all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</note>However God deales in truth, he ſeemes not at ſo much coſt for maintaining the World, as for making it. In nature we ſee every thing for its Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation requires a miraculous and divine hand, but planted once, God is not ſo conſpicuous; but leaves it to the ſoyle, as it were, to ſtand and grow by it ſelfe: and ſo it would ſeeme to fare even with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelfe, which is ſuch a ſuperſtruction above Nature; though it be planted by God, men muſt conſerve it. The Church is like the Garden of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> which God mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſet our Parents to dreſſe, and keepe it.</p>
            <p>The ſeverall formes of Religion which have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103554:3"/>ſwayed the world, in their times, (in pretence at leaſt) have felt his arme, and expected ours; his arme of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, and ours of munificence; that the riches, and braveries of this world, whereupon men ſet greateſt price, might adorne their doctrine; and not only the abſtract and ſtudious mindes, but ſenſuall affections al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thereby be muſd, and caught, and all our luſts there find repoſe. This is not only the myſtery of Antichriſt, and Idolatry, but the right of all Religion. The <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> at firſt had their Tabernacle, and its attendants, by Gods appointment, glorious, however <hi>Aarons</hi> inward devotion ſhone, his Veſtments and retinue too were very ſpecious: but the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the riches of the ſeverall orders of the Prieſts thereof ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive; and yet little enough to keep the people from Idolatry.</p>
            <p>And Chriſtianitie, as much as it excels all other Sects, for ought that wee know, can but expect the ſame lot. In planting of the Goſpell (indeed) God ſhewed himſelfe in ſignes and wonders; hee powred forth his Spirit, and accommodated it with a kindly ſoyle, the munificent affections of men, whereby it is growne in ſtate and glory.</p>
            <p>But though it was firſt propagated by ſuch ſedulity of the Spirit,, and God ſhewed himſelfe therein, as much as ever; though Chriſt hath promiſed the Holy Ghoſt, thereby to preſerve to himſelf a Church upon earth, unto the worlds end; wee now want the ſenſe and proof of Gods preſence, the Primitive times had; and may conceive he lookes not ſtill to be tempted to miracles: Divine and humane meanes muſt concur.</p>
            <p>That intereſt the Goſpell hath gotten, theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worldly braveries, after the plauſibleneſſe of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103554:4"/>doctrine it ſelfe, are the beſt evidence we have left for Chriſtianitie: the beſt, at leaſt, we have to ſhew to one another. Riches and honours now muſt ſerve for the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/>
               <note place="margin">The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and right of our Hierarchy.</note>Thoſe of the Ancient worthys that firſt propagated Chriſtianitie, had neither Dioceſſe nor Pariſh, but the wide world before them: they had nothing of their own, yet ſuch a Familiar had they of the Holy Ghoſt, they could want nothing. Then, all planting the ſame doctrine, every man had a care of all the Churches, and looked to the watering too of what was planted; and the people, as conſcious of the truth they heard, took ſpeciall order to preſerve the ſame amongſt them. Heroicke mindes not knowing in the world better how to beſtow their eſtates, in teſtimony of their affection, erected Churches, and endowed them with priviledges, gave them Tyths and Oblations, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a competence of maintenance, they added ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie, and with riches, gave honour and ſway to the Clergie. Kings as was fore-propheſied, became the Churches nurſing Fathers, and Queenes her nurſing Mothers. They made Religion the buſines of States, which now we make but a State inſtrument of. They had a care to fortifie Religion againſt the corruption of nature, and to recommend and ſeale their faith unto worſe times: as if by a holy kinde of Simony, they would purchaſe the Holy Ghoſt, and buy the Prince of darkneſſe out of his dominions. They priviledged Churchmen to their owne cognizance, to arme and hearten them againſt ſinne; that they might not only like Muſitians play for a benevolence; but that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates themſelves might not with more authoritie tranſgreſſe, than the Prieſt rebuke them. They held
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103554:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>up degrees in the Church, as objects ſtill for induſtry in the Prieſt, and reverence in the people; a reverence, which in a right way, halfe performes Religion. They conſtituted Biſhops, and Archbiſhops; Churchmen for Church affaires, one of moſt tryed truſt, and but one for expedition: where the Law is agreed upon, a ſingle eye may ſee Juſtice; or moſt eaſily anſwer for it. Biſhops for order at home, and Archbiſhops fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (if we ſhall not ſeeme to be led by ſounds) as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in metropoliſſes over other Biſhops, arches unto the King and unto forreigne Churches, that though States differ, the communion of Saints might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the Church might keep at unitie, and by uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted force repell hereſie.</p>
            <p>In no great Councell could the man of God bee baulked, that they might be ſure to ſerve God before themſelves; as ſecure, that while the Church proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and they had God amongſt them, all was ſafe: and in Courts of Conſcience, where the Lawes reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, they thought none ſo fit as the man of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ranked Biſhops and Archbiſhops in honour with Dukes and Barons. And theſe things were fixt and certaine, to avoid the feaver of a quotidian can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſe, and that in ſtanding counſell they might the more improve themſelves, and profit others; and the law of Chriſt and his Church, be ſure to receive no detriment; and for ſupply of mens mortalitie, they founded Colledges and Cathedrals. Thus they kept up mens hopes and Imaginations, making the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood anſwerably incomprehenſible with their God; and the Crowne received luſtre, in conjunction with the Miter. According to the rules of that great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect, they built <hi>Ad uſum, ad ſpeciem, &amp; ad firmita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:103554:5"/>an Hierarchie for uſe, and ſhew, and an Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie for durance, as firme as lawes could make it: as conſcious, that if the Clergie be ſo thin laid, that the people may looke through and round about it, it will ſoone fall into contempt, and Religion be exploded.</p>
            <p>Thus Chriſtianitie grew upon the world, mankind became throughly religious, and the Tempter was well nigh diſcouraged in his buſineſſe. This was the flouriſhing ſtate of Chriſts Church on earth, which we can only hope to have amended in Heaven. And herein, God be thanked, our Church of England had her ſhare</p>
            <p>Nor was this meerely matter of State, but a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Policie. The ancient ſtile of Grants and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for theſe matters, was <hi>Domino Deo noſtro of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferimus &amp; dicamus,</hi> we give them unto God. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, God as he inſtituted them, tooke them to himſelfe. For gifts and oblations he ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt give them me, Exod.</hi> 22.30. For Churches and Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, <hi>My Houſe, Mat.</hi> 21.13. For Tythes, <hi>Will a man rob God? Malach.</hi> 3.9. For Lands, <hi>Ye ſhall offer unto the Lord an holy portion, Ezek.</hi> 4 5.1. For their perſons and Honours, <hi>Touch not mine Annointed, nor doe my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets no harme, Pſal.</hi> 105.15. And the ſame Law, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preſſeth under the Goſpell, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18. Though we have ſome difference in the manner of Worſhip, Sacrifice and ſeverall Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies being aboliſhed; there is the ſame ſubſtance for Guides in Gods worſhip, which is the Reaſon of the Law, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in the name of the Lord foretold, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.21. <hi>And I will take of them for Priests and for Levites, ſaith the Lord:</hi> Prieſts hee ſaith, not meerely Laymen, nor meerely Prieſts, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103554:5"/>ſeverall degrees, Prieſts and Levites. This is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall branch of that honouring God with our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which is enjoyned, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9. what we relieve the poore with, is not ſo much our Almes, as their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igence; and as neceſſitie exacts it, it quickly periſheth. But theſe Donations, as they ſavour of a more inward and deeper Pietie, are of a more laſting ſubſtance. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the eternall Treaſures we lay up for our ſelves, we provide for the perpetuitie of Religion unto after Ages of men, and may be ſaid to honour God not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our ſelves, but in all wee gaine to honour him.</p>
            <p>But for the Hierarchie, becauſe that is moſt ſtuck at. Firſt, wee muſt conceive order and decency long before riches, and the favour of States in the Church. It was many Ages, and the Goſpell had a large ſpread, before Emperours were reclaimed to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie. And though wee have no ſpeciall rule from Chriſt himſelfe, for thoſe rounds of Order, but the Originall of our Church Government, through thoſe Miſts of times, bee ſcarce percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; If wee trace Epiſcopacy backwards (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the favours of the World came in by degrees) wee ſhall reſolve it upon the Apoſtles Age, and finde the like preſumptions in Reaſon for our Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as for our Sabboth. As the magnificence of the Jewiſh Church was commanded by God himſelfe; the ſame Providence, though in a ſecret way, would ſeeme to have introduced our Church Diſcipline. Our Saviour came rather to plant Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, than Government; that as abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary he provided for, and left-Government for the worke of time, and a Teſtimony of his Doctrines Approbation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103554:6"/>
            <p>Though he condemn'd the Ambition of honour in his Diſciples, more than to glorifie God thereby, and make them more beneficent and ſerviceable unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; never was there greater friend to order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, hee ſtood for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and hee ſtood for God, and would have the Scribes and Phariſees themſelves, in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire, obſerved. As him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aſſum'd the Title of Lord and Maſter, he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a <hi>Maximus</hi> and a <hi>Minimus</hi> amongſt his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo the greateſt became as the leaſt, to ſerve and miniſter to the reſt. At his departure, hee had many things to ſay unto his Diſciples, which then they could not beare, but the Holy Ghoſt hee promiſed them ſhould abide with them, and leade them into all truth: And ſecondly, bring to their remembrance whatſoever he had told them. What the many things wanting our Saviour meant, might be, is difficult. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicen Chriſtianam,</hi> Rules for private life hee had laid himſelfe, they would need only a Remembrancer for them. But <hi>Politia Eccleſiaſtica,</hi> this point of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, for Church government, ſeemes a truth as then untaught; and being ſuch a maine thing, and requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time to make the World capable of it, me thinks we ſhould hold a reverend eſteeme of what wee finde ſo ſetled; whether by the Apoſtles, or their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. The Holy Ghoſt was ſufficient warrant for the Apoſtles, and the abiding of the Holy Ghoſt, ſuggeſts a regard to their Succeſſors, and hereunto perhaps that ſpeech is to be referred, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Lo, I am with you allway even to the end of the World.</hi> Popiſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies as they have not the like neceſſitie, nor the like antiquitie, have not the like plea with govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Humilitie garniſhed with miracles, or a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103554:6"/>humilitie, which our Saviour himſelfe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, was the likelieſt way in reaſon, at firſt for the planting of the Goſpell of humilitie. It was reverend in it ſelfe, and unlike to provoke the jealouſie of States: honour comes kindely eſt of it ſelf, and ſhews moſt glorious when it is rather found than ſought. Yet it is Gods owne promiſe, that he that humbleth himſelfe ſhould be exal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed. It is the honour of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, that it could deſerve honour while it diſpiſed it. As the people would have taken our Saviour, and made him King, 'tis like they faſtened favours upon his followers. And miracles ceaſing, the legall aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome Church diſcipline was in reaſon wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Acceptation. It cannot bee doubted, but the Apoſtles were the Patriarchs or Grandfathers of the Church. The number of twelve was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Myſterie, and the preciſe ſupply of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in the Election of <hi>Matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> proves a prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in them, above the Seven it Diſciples. As they begot ſons to God, they adopted fellow labourers into their Miniſterie, ſuch (no doubt) as obſerved their Fathers while they lived, and ſo farre approved of the benefit of that order they found under them, that they maintain'd it after their diſſolutions. As the twelve were call'd firſt, the Evangeliſts make ſpeciall mention of their names, and their families, as whom they ought to honour. They were more converſant with Chriſt, and more inſtructed by him, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with him unto the end. And after his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he applyed himſelfe eſpecially to them. Then hee renewed their Commiſſion with a <hi>Sicut miſit me Pater,</hi> to boote, which may extend to Juriſdiction and Ordination; Ordination of the Clergie, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103554:7"/>over the whole Church; and to enable them for ſuch ſervice, he made good his promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt, and gave them power of binding and looſing ſins. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> I am ſure aſſumed this Authority to himſelfe, hee counted himſelfe a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-builder, whoſe office is to order the worke, and command inferiour Workmen: hee exerciſed a Legiſlative power; hee excommunicated (for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) the Inceſtuous Perſon, and againe reſtored him; as may bee ſeene in his Epiſtles, which all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with Canons and Conſtitutions Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. This power of ordering Church affaires, hee further propagated to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Titus;</hi> as appeares in the Rules and directions to them. And ſo (for it would be tedious to name particulars) it would ſeeme to have beene derived to our times. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our forme of Church Government came from the light of nature, and the Iewiſh patterne (for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon extols it,<note place="margin">See B. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews Anal.</note> and * there is a correſpondence between the Jewiſh and the Chriſtian Hierarchie,) or from a ſpeciall Illumination and motion of the Spirit of God; (which the former times exceld in) it is as needleſſe, as hard to diſtinguiſh, perhaps all concur'd, however Chriſt we ſee,<note place="margin">See Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maghs O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig.</note>
               <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.20. * approves of ſuch Biſhops, and honours them with the Title of Starres, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels (as Diabolicall as ſome would make them) and * <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> themſelves could not but approve of this Government,<note place="margin">See Maſons additions.</note> and (waveing the name) came as neere unto an Epiſcopall forme as the iniquitie of their times would admit. Though we determine not, whether <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> or <hi>humano,</hi> It will ſuffice us E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy is rightly conſtituted.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103554:7"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> It were to be wiſhed indeed our Doctrine had ſtill the ſame Primitive Teſtimony,<note place="margin">The Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to bee wiſht, not expected.</note> and our Miniſtery that viſible Aſſiſtance of Divinity, the firſt times of the Church enjoyed; which a <hi>Simon Magus</hi> could prize above riches, which ſhewed men nearer favourites with God, than riches make them with Kings; which might confound, and ſtop the mouthes of all gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, and all men be wholly convinced and compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to obedience. But we can no more expect theſe now, than they at firſt could challenge our Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
            <p>Such aſſiduity and open violence of the Spirit, though neceſſary for times otherwiſe anticipated, where Chriſtianity hath once advanced its banners and engaged the world, would render our Faith not worth God ha' mercy.</p>
            <p>That humble temper and exemplary lowlineſſe of Spirit, could our Church aſſuredly bee furniſhed with it, hath a winning grace, and bravery above State. Heathens have ſeene its beauty, and beene enamour'd on it. But its chiefeſt efficacy is with minds already pious, which (God knowes) is the ſmalleſt part of mankinde, and ſuch Ornaments being at no certainty, no not in Church-men, ſuch ſupplements as may bee had, for eſtabliſhing Religion, are to bee allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
            <p>It was our Saviours owne Precept to his Diſciples, <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents, but innocent as Doves,</hi> Chriſtianity and Policy, the wiſedome of Serpents, and the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of Doves, may ſtand together, and while wee are but as ſheepe amongſt wolves, it is but neceſſary they ſhould. The leaders that are upon ſuch hard ſervice, had need have the beſt proviſion, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103554:8"/>beſt order, that may bee, the beſt to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and advance the Church. Forreigne plants we know are choyce, and require a ſpeciall care, and Chriſtianity being ſuch a ſupernaturall ſtem, will need; and being ſo Noble, will deſerve our beſt foſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>When God ſends Angels Embaſſadors to men, hee puts them in humane ſhapes, the better to comply with human nature. But when men are to act <hi>Gods</hi> part, they had need put on all the Divinity that may be. Riches and honours are not oppoſite to humility, but make more conſpicuous. Though a Divine ſhew more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred without either ſtaffe, or ſcrip, as hee that hath wholly caſt off this world, for his hopes in another; a knap-ſacke and ſword now is thought no luggage; whilſt we are men, and moſt part fleſh and bloud, the Elements we conſiſt of would find ſome likely nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſupports of this life, not wholly bee neglected. It was a ſad, but ſage conſideration of the Poet,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quis virtutem amplectitur ipſam,</l>
               <l>Praemia ſi tollas? —</l>
            </q>
            <p>We would have a Learned and Religious Clergie, otherwiſe wee have ſmall hopes they ſhould make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuch; but we ſhall hardly find learning or Piety flouriſh without theſe encouragements. To paſſe by the improbity of Poverty, which is far above that of plenty; Though knowledge as the light of the ſoule, for it ſelfe be deſirable, men ſteare not thitherward, unleſſe their other deſires be otherwiſe ſatisfied, or learning ſeeme the meanes to ſatisfie them. Or how forward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103554:8"/>ſoever they may bee to learne, to make them teach, they muſt yet have ſome further incentive. Or though good natures might ſo farre exalt their mindes, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Parents, while it is in their power, will be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry how they dedicate and breed up a ſon to a ſtudious beggery. We muſt expect Prieſts, with a curſe, of the loweſt of the people, or the halt and the maimed out of greater families, if Divinity and the ſervice of God cannot advance, like the Law, or the ſword, or one of the twenty foure companies. The gifts of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, of infallibility, and Propheſiing ceaſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect wee the Spirit of ſelfe-denyall as freſh as ever? The wiſeſt Law-givers have beene wont to conſider men, <hi>In maſsa corrupta,</hi> averſe from all good, and only to be reclaimed by reward, and puniſhment: and hath this laſt thrifty Age diſcovered a new way, to put theſe accounts upon the world to come? Or only to be liberall in her puniſhments? Thoſe that travaile to <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> what ſatisfaction ſoever they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe themſelves, at their Journies end, are glad to turne in ſometimes by the way, and refreſh themſelves in other Cities, and meaner Innes; and by ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet ſtayes, haſten their courſe.</p>
            <p>Such a Journey have wee to that heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> (a Journey I account it, not an anxious Pilgrimage,) though the reſt we promiſe our ſelves there, be above all the repaſts of the way, and thoſe eſpecially that convert ſinners, have the aſſurance to ſhine like Starres in the Firmament; to ſupport fraile nature, and keepe a ſenſe of what wee expect, the hoſpitality of this world is intended us. Though our devotion lye for Heaven, Riches, Honours, and pleaſures, all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this light may bee our bayting places; ſo wee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103554:9"/>make this world but as the City we paſſe through, not inhabit; and theſe braveries but as vyands to refreſh, not luggage to hinder our journey. This world is an honeſt Inne, the inordinate Affections, and dotage of the gueſts, make a brothell of it. Could our guides ſuſtaine themſelves with the hopes of the world to come, it muſt needs put mettle into us. Who would not more cheerefully follow ſuch Leaders? and could our Law-givers be exemplary herein, it might excite our guides. But they being of the ſame mold with us, why ſhould we expect it? why ſhould wee ſtomacke them the repaſt we allow our ſelves? and looke that they ſhould forfeite all for us? It argues diſproportioned mindes, to affect ſuch diſproportion. We muſt not ſtand on what we would have, but what is juſt, and equall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> Since then Religion is ſuch a ground of happineſſe, and riches and honors,<note place="margin">The ſin of Sacriledge.</note> now ſuch maine props of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; juſtly hath Sacriledge, or the diminution here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, beene ever accounted the higheſt, the boldeſt and the damnableſt ſin in the world. Supplant Religion, and we diſſolve all the tyes betwixt God and men; we weigh anchor, and fall to Sea again, the Sea of vulgar paſſions. Other miſchiefes have their limits, they hurt but one or other, and there is an end. But this ſtrikes at goodnes it ſelfe, it ſets the world beſides its hinges, &amp; ſweeps our peace from off the earth God, the King, and all of us, are thereby damnified. He hath a heart of Iron, a ſalvage, and Cyclopike breaſt, that can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade Heaven and rob God, that can pull downe the Prerogative of the King, and his Crowne too, and ſpoyle mankind of their ſafety. Heathens themſelves have alwayes had more reverence to things dedicated
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103554:9"/>unto their gods, and to violate but the Religion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countryes, though much more vaine than their owne, looked ſo monſtrous, that it was ever accounted inauſpicious; and the wrongs done to a falſe Deity, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed an horror with it, and was uſually revenged by the true one. Hiſtories abound with ſuch monuments, and it was long ere this crime was knowne in Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> Yet now, though we love not to ſpeake plainely of Church riches, there are foure Colours for Sacriledge;<note place="margin">The colours for Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled.</note> Revenge, conſcience, convenience, and covetouſneſſe; which together, and a part, threaten havocke.</p>
            <p>Firſt, (for our angry Paſſions uſually lead in theſe tumultuary courſes) men cry out upon the inſolence of the Biſhops, that they have ſeverall times endangered the liberty of the State; and now they have them in their power, they will root out them. <hi>Rome,</hi> the truth is, <hi>Rome</hi> the place of the Imperiall ſeate, hath given ground for ſuch reaſoning. When it enjoyed all the happineſſe this life is capable of, it grew exorbitant. That ſtate which ſeem'd above forreigne caſualty, laboured with its owne happineſſe, and from its height (which is the courſe of worldy things) found way to ebbe againe.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops there too conſcious of their own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the influence they had upon the State, not content with their Primacy, abuſed Religion into Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; and caſting off all moderation, the Pope devoured the Emperour. Thus the Head of the Church degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into a monſter, and drew the whole world after him. In reaching at Temporall Sovereignty, he broke the Spirituall unity, and the wound got the obduration to become incurable; hee diſdaining once to come to the barre as a delinquent, having power to his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103554:10"/>
            <p>I defend not <hi>Rome,</hi> nor ſhall I excuſe our owne late Biſhops. Liberty is our common birth-right, which ought to be deare unto us next our Faith. But their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, whatſoever we conceive it, hath not beene ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, I hope, as to pollute all they touched, ſo that Epiſcopacie, the office it ſelfe, cannot again be hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Though Biſhops have abuſed their power to oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (oppreſſion, which is the proper ſin of Power) this world is no ſtate of perfection, other men will doe as much; the abuſe of things muſt not take away their uſe. By that Rule we ſhall neither have Magiſtrate, nor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in that all have ſinned. To decry an Office, an office (as hath been ſhewen) rightly inſtituted, for ſome men in it, is an Act for mad men, not for Legiſlators; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cannot be in earneſt. It were a courſe to deale with an enemy, when we have him in our Power, to make ſure work. But God and our ſelves are herein intereſt. Offices are Gods, though men are in them, and God catcheth not advantages againſt us. Laſtly, our revenge will light upon our own pates, we ſhall pull out our own eyes, and daſh out our own brains. We ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſoone find and rue the loſſe of ſuch order. If we feare the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Biſhops themſelves, we conſider not we have a Gracious King, and ſhal have Parliaments to do Juſtice. If we feare their drawing towards <hi>Rome,</hi> we forget our Praemunire. If we feare their ſetting up the King, their will be more feare of more active Inſtruments. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be left to God, and the goodnes of Princes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſome from our Saviours words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8 <hi>But be not yee called Rabbi, &amp;c.</hi> damne all ſuperintenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in men in holy orders, as unlawfull and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. But all the world may ſee, it is the Phariſaicall vain-glorious Affectation to be magnified of men, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.6. not the Authority, or the title and preheminence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103554:10"/>to God-ward, is here forbidden. And otherwiſe, the Precept (being given to the people and the Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 1.) will ſerve to pull down temporall Lords, and the Presbyterians too as well as Biſhops. Nor is there any reaſon the rule, <hi>vos autem non ſic,</hi> when it is laid betwixt the Princes of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Diſciples alone, <hi>Ch.</hi> 20.27. (as here betwixt the Phariſees and the multitude) ſhould carry a harder interpretation.</p>
            <p>Though the Diſciples onely happened to be preſent, when mother <hi>Zebede</hi> gave the occaſion of the words, they were men by nature, how ever Diſciples by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and when we extend prohibitions to them beyond their perſons, they uſually repreſent not Miniſters alone but all Chriſtians whatſoever: vice may bee more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly in Clergy men, but it is as unlawful in all <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> But againſt the power and authority of Divines in Temporall affaires, they further preſſe the practice of the Apoſtles <hi>Acts</hi> 6.2. and Reaſon from thence, That it is too much for Divines to be knowing men in buſines of eſtate, and to underſtand the Rules and Lawes of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But firſt, the proviſion for the poore, about which the queſtion is, was laid at the Apoſtles feete, to be diſtributed by them, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.35. Secondly, though the Apoſtles thought not meet to leave the word of <hi>God</hi> wherewith the world, as yet was not acquainted, to wait on Tables, which was below their miniſtery; It ſhewes their underſtanding, and authority, in that they gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for fit Stewards and Overſeers. Thirdly, theſe men make Divines men of too narrow capacities, and ſet Gods Law and mans at too great diſtance, If States-men have ſoules to bee ſaved, whereunto the Miniſtery may contribute. If the heathen Oratour muſt be ſeen in all the arts, and nooks of learning, the Chriſtian Doctor had need bee bard no field of knowledge, for the ſoule
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103554:11"/>he is to look to, is thrice more worth than the goods of Fortune. Our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> and all it ſeems are out, who take their Church-men along in their weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyeſt affaires, and their Sermons here in <hi>England</hi> they ſay ſavoured of ſome thing more than pure preaching of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>The Clergie are men, men of liberall education, they wade through the Arts, ere they come at divinity, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (me thinks) they ſhould be capable of human affaires with other men. And Divinity can bee no hinderance. Perhaps they are better ſeene in Eccleſiaſticall matters, and therefore may arrogate them as their peculiar, but for us to exclude them our Councells, as an abject ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, who have the deepeſt ſhare in Gods promiſe of aſſiſtance, and give the beſt Authority to reſolutions, comming in the Name of God, cannot proceed either from good policy or Religion. The Prieſt-hood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> had a hand in all Temporall affaires, and in matters meerely of order and governement, and no way Typicall, <hi>Iewes</hi> (as hath beene ſaid) may bee Preſidents for Chriſtians. The Apoſtles perhaps at firſt exerciſed none other Authority but the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power of excommunication, to withhold the Ordinances, and forbid Communion which delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and left further cenſures to the Secular Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. But when Princes received the Goſpell, they requited the Miniſters thereof with a ſhare of their power, and magnified their authority with the glory of theſe Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Perhaps it had been ſinne in them at firſt not to have honoured the Goſpell: but for us to deveſt it, is more out of queſtion.</p>
            <p>Their Voyces in Parliament, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> may ſeeme mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſmall moment, for the publike peace. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103554:11"/>the diſhonour to Religion, they are of dangerous conſequence, for the ſame reaſon that ſhall invalid them, may as well overthrow the whole Fabrick of the Church. And it is to be feared it is ſome mens aime to effect that by degrees, which at once they find not feaſable. The Prelate ſpoke not by rote, who ſaid they would ſerve them as High-way men doe honeſt Travellers, firſt gag, and bind, then rifle them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they pretend a convenience in pulling down Order and Government in the Church, to buy in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations, and ſet up preaching. Preaching in deede and labouring in the Word have high Attributes in Scripture, as of introducing grace, and working faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Goſpell at firſt being committed to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes of men, the only way then of propagating thereof was Sermon-wiſe, by a kinde of Preaching, Chriſt thus taught the people, and inſtituted his Diſciples to this Annunciation. But their preaching was not the ſame in uſe with us, theirs had its Authoritie from the Spirit, they ſpake by, which wee borrow from their writings. Any way of publiſhing and promoting the Goſpell, is preaching in the Scriptures ſenſe, as well as our expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Scripture, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> involves them all, nor can the foreſaid Attributes, be appropriated to that which we call preaching. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> laboured in the Goſpell, before there was a Goſpell written; hee laboured by word and writing, by conſtituting Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and in ſeeing them obſerv'd: and now not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Expoſitions, but all effectuall meanes for the propagation of the Tenor thereof, is the Ordinance of God, and no doubt his free Spirit accordingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth grace and faith by them: Whether they bee Doctrinall, by word, and writing, by catechiſme to young beginners, by reading of the Scriptures, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryphall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103554:12"/>Bookes, divine Homilies, or other profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcourſes: or after inſtitution magiſteriall by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting and eſtabliſhing good lawes, as Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours (we know) being converted, by their Edicts, in an inſtant, more advanced the Goſpell, than pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Preachers with many Sermons in many ages, though otherwiſe they had extraordinary aſſiſtance of the Spirit. The Goſpell may and muſt be preach'd in every Court, that is, Chriſts law muſt be there preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and though that bee not the proper place for teaching, there may happen to bee as effectuall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for the promotion of the Goſpell, from the Bench, as from the Pulpit, where men of power meet and draw things to a point, there, there is preaching po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull. Thus ſome particular Biſhops have had the oportunitie to doe more good, than all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie in their Dioceſſe againe. Neither in words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but in workes of pietie, and buſineſſe of State, Chriſt may be advanced, Lay-men may, but Miniſters more eſpecially muſt, thus Evangelize. Our preaching and practiſing, and writing, and Government, are all twines of that Mother preaching in Scripture: Let preaching be the eldeſt and the faireſt ſiſter; their dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and their vertues may be alike, we muſt not ſet too great a price on one, to diſparage the reſt; or becauſe preaching was firſt of all, reduce Chriſtianity to its prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and hold there. This were, as if becauſe Writing was before Printing, and then had high elogies amongſt the ancients, we ſhould renounce the benefit of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to hold to Writing only, or prefer it before Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. This is the grand impoſture and illuſion of the Age. Preaching is cryed up, nought but Preaching, God knowes a ſorry kind of Preacding, when nobler helpes ſhould ſhare. Its to bee feared they would ſerve the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103554:12"/>Clergie, as the Fox in the fable did the Crow, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their voices, till they let goe their morſells: where wee heare knowledge is confined, wee cannot thinke <hi>libertas Prophetandi,</hi> ſhall have its ſcope. As in Reaſon we excell beaſts: Elocution, whereby we readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt conveigh our conceit to others, exalts us amongſt men. Sermons may be moſt appoſite to the maladies of the hearers; and beſt fit for their affections, they moſt readily catch, and tranſport furtheſt. The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, like as skillfull Phyſition, can varie his <hi>recipe</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the exigence of the patient: hee can caſt his diſcourſe into what mould or forme he pleaſe: he can inſinuate, and creepe upon particulars, how ever prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd, and as occaſion ſerves, invade or ſurp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe the Affections: he can give food to healthy, and phyſick to diſeaſed minds. And the very act of Preaching, the countenance and geſture, adde life to words, and have a ſingular energie over bare reading; for thus they make all they deliver new, as it were, and their owne; when the other way it ſeemes but flat, and borrowed; they ſet forth Chriſt and his Doctrine with more pompe unto our ſoules: and in preſſing Scripture make it like bruiſed Spices, more raviſhing. Yet its long of us, and our corrupt affections, if Sermons car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it; we are more for ſauce than meate, more tickled with the momentany dreſſe, and reliſh of the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, than the meate which endureth. As diſeaſes are commonly alike in different men, the ſame reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were wee attentive might ſerve our ſeverall ſoules, as doe our bodies. God no doubt was both able and willing to preſcribe Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, for all our Maladies in his Word: and Men uſually more ſufficiently expreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by writing, than by word of mouth;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103554:13"/>upon deliberation, than on the ſuddaine; nay, extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary diſcourſes, like our actions, are ſubject to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy, and oft times derogate from the Majeſtie of Scripture, and the evidence of the Spirit therein: So that Government, and good lawes, had need to order all; and the Scripture is that all muſt bee ordered by. It is bare Text alone that gives the minde repoſe, and grounds beliefe. As we confine not our ſelves only to ſet formes of doctrine, to ſtint the Spirit; It is good we ſhould have ſome things ſet and fixt to ſtint humane extravagancies: leſt Religion become meerely mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Phanſy, and the Church be converted into a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. It were ingratitude againſt the Spirit, to ſlight ſuch grounds as he hath laid us; and preſumption ſtill whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to relye on him: but the middle way, to hold ſome thing certaine, and attend his further motions is ſafe. Preaching, and practice, and writing, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are all uſefull in the Church towards others, yet where wee have but the Goſpell it ſelfe read, none of them is abſolutely neceſſarie to ſalvation. But if wee muſt compare them, though they are beſt together, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to us now, is no leſſe neceſſary than that which we call preaching. It extends it ſelfe to a larger forme, and it is that muſt keepe preaching and all in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Preaching may bee more neceſſary for the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Church, but government, as it is more noble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is more neceſſary where a Church is planted. The Church of Chriſt is never ſo ſetled, but it is militant here on earth, and had need of the beſt marſhalling in ranke and fyle: The enemy will finde a gap, or where to make one, if there bee not ſome Generall to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke, ſome Commander to ride the round, and ſee the watch ſet, one that for place, and power, need not feare the face of man. Unleſſe we diſlike our Religion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103554:13"/>there is no reaſon we ſhould find fault with our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If Religion have not much of the image of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in it, a ſword ſometimes to determine us, aſwell as a ballance to weigh truth, her ballance will be deſpiſed. As I have no faith in charmes, I am not wholly for preaching, that bare talking way, without the Spirit, is not like government, to ſettle men in an habituate courſe of pietie. It rather puzzels the beliefe, than actuates our obedience. But with degrees of promotion, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and learning, and ſo preaching it ſelfe, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily fall. And the more ordinate Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the more concentrate to unitie it is, it agreeth better with Monarchy, and holds better harmony with its head, which is Chriſt. In the office of a Biſhop, an Archbiſhop, or a Patriarch, as ſtrange as it may ſound, <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelfe could ſee no hurt, while they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto Chriſt, an Emperour, and a generall Councell.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt.</hi> 4.4 4.</note> And how far the like were not againe to be endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, were a diſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiſion becoming ſtates truly Chriſtian, for by this means, as the promiſe of Chriſt to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſhould have its regard, ſtates might enjoy the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions of the whole Church, though they retaine the liberty of admitting or rejecting their Counſels. It is ſeene in all eſtates, <hi>Quae communiter poſsidentur commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter negliguntur,</hi> the very dividing is the deſtruction of power; what can an ordinary man do? or who will care for ſhewing himſelfe in commotions, when the danger ſhall be his owne, and many muſt ſhare in the honour? Let not men flatter themſelves too much in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of changing the uſe of riches without taking them from the Church, though things perhaps may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter carried both amongſt Biſhops, and downe to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Clergie, there may be rapine in honours aſwell as in riches, If we take them from God and Religion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103554:14"/>though we cannot convert them to our-ſecular uſes: If there be leſſe of private advantage, there may be more of malic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in it: but there may be of advantage, in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe others, to get into their places. <hi>Abſalon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had other pretences, when in his heart he ſaid, <hi>O that I were made judge in the Land.</hi> But it concernes them that but alter things conſecrate, to be ſure it be to the better; for the ſcandall of innovation goes further than the thing reformed. <hi>Mutato Sacerdotio mutatur etiam &amp; Lex,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, and the diſhonouring of the Prieſt hood will expoſe it to contempt, and in the end, its to be feared, prove the bane of Religion. I condemne not Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>che, which have not, or cannot arrive at our happineſſe; for there is great odds, <hi>inter Eccleſiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituendam, &amp; conſtitutam.</hi> Pietie is the principall, and as we condemne no Church that holds but that <hi>unum neceſſarium</hi> of Pietie, ſo mee thinkes none ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne us for aſſerting of Pietie, by ſo regular govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But it is fitter they aſpire to our ſtate, than think of reducing us to their condition: with us that of <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ananias</hi> muſt take place, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. <hi>While it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained was it not thine owne? but now thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not men but God.</hi> It is a fearefull ſentence of God to <hi>Samuel,</hi> upon the <hi>Iſraelites, Sam.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Hearken unto the voice of the People — for they have not reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thee, but they have rejected mee, that I ſhould reigne over them.</hi> If <hi>Nemo poteſt mutare conceſſum in alterius praejudicium,</hi> ſhall wee without licence from God, take away what was truly given him? This breach how ſmall ſoever at a part, will open a gap to all the Churches patrimony: And though it bee but matter of Diſcipline we talke of; I pray God ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to the diſcipline, entrench not ſoone upon the Doctrine it ſelfe, and bring that in queſtion. Though
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103554:14"/>our neighbours of <hi>Scotland</hi> and the Low Countryes, though the emulation of adverſaries, as yet keepe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; with their forme of government; When in cold bloud we ſhall feele the inconveniences even of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed diſcipline, as they call it; and conſider how much we have been out; I pray God we come not to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> or <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> as now it is, ſo find the way to us. For who ſhall animate Princes for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when the Prieſt muſt keep at diſtance? This que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in <hi>England</hi> will be of dangerous conſequence in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſuch prophane ones as ſpoyle for the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, how ever they pleaſe themſelves in their fury, will one day finde a curſe goe along with their prey, which like <hi>Achans</hi> execrable thing, will ruine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their families. They forfeit their confidence in a providence, and that comfort in their brethren and their own breaſts, which ſhould be their life and ſtay, in time of trouble. They uſually dye forlorne of God, and men, miſerable, diſconſolate, and deteſted: and yet have more to anſwer for in the world to come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">IX. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note>The Church of <hi>England</hi> (God be thanked) yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the face of a Church. How ever for riches and honours, ſhe comes ſhort of her ſelfe in former times, ſhe comes behind few Churches in Chriſtendome. We have tythes and oblations, Biſhops and governours, rich Colledges and Cathedrals, large priviledges &amp; endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſuch as might make men that like not our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, fall in love with our diſcipline, and in admiring theſe glories, adore the Divinity that provok'd them. She is like the Vine of God in the 80. Pſalm. <hi>O let not the wild Bore out of the Forreſt breake downe her branches, nor the little Foxes devoure her grapes.</hi> If we have neither ſo much Piety nor Policy as to contribute to the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103554:15"/>of our order abroad, nor the promoting of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion at home; nor to make ſatisfaction to the Church (as the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> would have it) for the wrongs of our forefathers. Let us not be guilty of ſo much Atheiſm, as to withdraw its maintenance. Let us not let goe our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorage, and caſt our ſelvs upon the fluctuations of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If the Clergy in its height have abuſed theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to their worldly ends (as all eſtates on earth are ſubject to abuſe) If their happineſſe have made them wanton. If to the keyes and their ſpirituall ſword, they be catching at the Temporall, and there be ſomething in their honours, which may occaſion them to looke to <hi>Rome</hi>-ward: Let the curbe of Law hold them to their way, and the Trienniall Review look as auſtere on them as on Projectors. What reſtiveneſſe ſoever they have contracted, let proviſion bee made by wholſome diſcipline to reclaime them, but withhold not their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender to abate their ſervice. Let us not purſue Vices or Perſons ſo far as to violate offices, offices which have not contracted ſuch guilt, but they may be regenerated. Let us not defeate the charity of our pious Predeceſſors. Let us not diſhonour our State, and the Age we live in. Let us not rob Religion of its Ornaments, the Prieſt of his Reverence, and God of his Glory. In a word, let us not ſo flye from <hi>Rome,</hi> as to fall into the mouth of Hell, and rob God, to enrich the Devill againe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
